THE ARTIST JOHAN BORG
DISAPPEARED SOME YEARS AGO
WITHOUT A TRACE , FROM HIS HOME
ON THE ISLAND OF BALTRUM
IN THE FRISIAN ISLANDS .
HIS WIFE ALMA
LATER LEFT ME JOHAN 'S DIARY ,
WHICH SHE HAD FOUND
AMONG HIS PAPERS .
THIS DIARY AND ALMA 'S ACCOUNT ARE THE BASIS OF THIS FILM .
Can someone move that chair ?
And lower that a little ...
HOUR OF THE WOLF
A FILM BY INGMAR BERGMAN
Have you been ...
Listen , we 're not quite finished yet .
No ? All right .
Quiet , all ! Rolling !
Take !
Camera !
And begin .
No ...
I have nothing more to tell .
I 've given you the diary .
And you wonder why I choose to stay on here ?
We 've lived in this house together almost seven years .
Come winter , I can move to the mainland ,
work at the store as I have done before
when money was short .
The baby is due in a month , the doctor has said .
He examined me in May ,
before the very last time we came out here .
It was on a Friday , I remember .
It was quite late ...
about 10 : 00 , I think .
But it was still light out .
We 'd planned to stay here until August .
We were going to be completely alone .
He didn 't want to see another human being here .
He was afraid .
He liked that I was quiet .
He liked ...
We got here at about 3 : 00 in the morning .
We found a wheelbarrow in a shed on the beach .
When we got here , we were happy to see the apple tree in blossom .
Then we discovered footprints
under the kitchen window in the flower bed .
It annoyed Johan ,
but we forgot about it , because ...
Yes , we were happy .
We were happy to be home in our own house again .
Johan was uneasy .
He always grew anxious when his work did not go well ,
and it had not gone well for some time now .
And he became sleepless .
He was frightened , as if he was afraid of the dark .
It had gotten worse in the last few years .
- I know what . - What ?
- I 'm going to draw you . - No !
- Yes ! - Oh , no .
- Please let me ! - No .
- Yes , if you sit over there . - No .
Oh , come on now . Go on , Fatso !
- Here ? - A little farther back ... there .
- Are you cold ? - No .
I knew that .
So sit , just sit like you always do .
Don 't straighten up .
And pull the coat down a little over your shoulder ...
just like that , and pull your hair up
so I can see your neck better .
Fine , that 's right . And where are my glasses ?
And the damned bow is broken again .
There , can you sit just like that a moment ?
If day after day ,
I patiently drew you ...
Hello !
Now , look ...
I haven 't shown these to anyone .
You see , I made sketches of them !
This is the one who turns up most often .
And he 's almost harmless .
I think he 's homosexual .
And then there 's the old lady ,
the one always threatening to take off her hat .
Do you know what happens if she does ?
Her face comes off along with it , you see .
And here ...
He 's the worst of the lot .
I call him the Bird Man .
I don 't know if it 's a real beak or only a mask .
He 's so strangely quick ...
and he 's related to Papageno of The Magic Flute .
And the others !
The meat-eaters , the insects ...
and especially the spider men .
Here , the schoolmaster , his pointer in his trousers .
And then all the cast-iron , cackling women .
You must stay awake a little while longer .
In just an hour or so it will be dawn ...
and then I can sleep .
A minute is actually an immense space of time .
Wait , here it starts .
Ten seconds .
These seconds ...
You see how long they last ?
The minute isn 't over yet !
Ah , finally .
It 's gone now .
Say something .
Talk to me , Alma .
Hey , you ...
there 's something I 've thought about for a long time .
Are you listening ?
We 've lived together for seven years now ...
No , that 's not what I was going to say .
Now I know .
Isn 't it true that old people who have lived a lifetime together
start to resemble each other ?
They finally share so much ,
their thoughts and their faces take on the same expression .
Why do you think that is ?
I hope we will get so old that we ...
think each other 's thoughts ...
and we get little , dried-up ,
identical wrinkled faces .
What do you think about that ?
Are you sleeping ?
Come now .
Let 's go to bed now .
Okay .
Don 't look so frightened , child .
I 'm not dangerous .
Give me your hand .
Well ?
Can you feel my hand now ?
My fingers ,
the veins under my skin ?
At my age , the hands can get a little cold .
I am , after all , 216 years old .
No , what am I saying ?
Seventy-six , I mean .
No , I had better be on my way now .
Now , what was it I was going to say ?
Now I remember .
In his black satchel under the bed ,
there 's the sketchbook with drawings ...
Tell him not to do that .
And then one more thing .
He hides his diary in the same satchel .
Read it !
No , no !
DIARY
Wednesday , July 22nd .
I have recently been ill .
Not seriously , but unpleasant enough .
Pardon the interruption , but I have pondered for days
how most appropriately I might approach you .
I deemed it most polite to get directly to the point .
My name is Von Merkens , Baron Von Merkens .
Borg .
As you may know , I own this island .
I live in the old castle on the north side .
Would you and your wife care to join us
for a simple family supper ?
That 's kind of you .
It will be very simple , but I 'll give you a good wine .
And our salmon fishing is renowned .
Good-bye .
I should also say that my wife and I
are among your admirers , your ... fondest admirers .
Thursday , July 27th .
A very warm , hazy day .
I am still sickly after my illness .
Do you see this mark ?
Be more careful , my love ,
or it will end in disaster .
Don 't you remember ? I was leaving for a party ,
and I was wearing my green brocade dress .
Afterwards , I had such trouble putting my hair up again !
And then I forgot my gloves .
I have something I must speak to you about .
I 've received a letter that I must show you .
It was sent yesterday .
And here is what it says ...
" You do not see us , but we see you .
" The most horrible things can happen .
" Dreams can become unveiled .
The end is near ... "
" The wells will run dry ,
" and other fluids will moisten your white loins .
Thus is it decided . "
I almost became ill reading it .
How hot your hands are .
Do you have a fever ?
Before I see you , I always get so wound up .
Can you understand that ?
I wander as if in a dream the whole afternoon .
All my chores become so unreal and meaningless .
Be so kind as to help me with the zipper in my dress .
It always gets caught .
A strong wind indeed ! But magnificent , is it not ?
This place must be a painter 's dream or what ?
I 've lived here for quite a while .
One returns to the scene of the crime , so to speak ,
and commits new crimes !
You appear to be tired . Don 't over-exert yourself .
I mean , at our age , a certain caution is to be advised .
Youth is of tougher mettle .
I happen to know .
My name is Heerbrand , psychiatric curator .
I finger people 's souls and turn their insides out .
What do we see then ? I hardly need to tell you .
As an artist , you know the human heart .
What don 't you see in your facial studies ,
not to mention in your self-portraits ?
Why do you look at me like that ? Did I anger you ?
Your nerves out of sorts ? Something plaguing you ?
Shut up !
I think I need to ask you for more money .
What you gave me this month is almost gone .
We must pay the store next time we go to the mainland .
The bill is 176.50 , and then there 's the milk .
Don 't just shovel over money like that .
You have to look at my accounting !
It 's quite important , at least to me .
I received 500 on the 3rd .
You bought me that blanket , rather expensive ... 35 .
But it 's warm and lovely when I lie alone .
And here 's the previous bill from the store .
It 's high because we had to buy flour , sugar , and canned goods .
Comes to over 200 kronor ... 219 .
And there 's pocket money and stamps
and a chain for my bicycle
and new radio batteries ...
and the potato peeler ...
then soap , washing powder , a nail brush .
You need a new toothbrush . The one you have looks horrible .
- No . - Well , it does .
Then 50 kronor for your boy 's birthday .
And postage ... 75 öre .
That 's about 500 kronor .
7,36 .
You can count it to be sure .
We 're invited to the castle on Friday .
I know .
How do you know that ?
Good evening .
My wife Corinne .
You 're very welcome . Welcome .
My mother Countess Von Merkens .
My brother Ernst .
A pleasure . A pleasure .
Here is Archivist Lindhorst .
Delighted . I am one of your fondest admirers .
And this is Curator Heerbrand .
A pleasure . I believe we 've met already .
Would you like a drink ?
- May I serve a little ... - Yes , by all means .
The summer heat makes you so thirsty .
So how long have you been there ?
I thought you had been living here for months ,
we 've been hearing about you for so long !
Time flies so quickly ! Delighted you could come .
Damned awful housemaid . But she 's cheap , of course .
My brother cannot afford better .
I would like you all to observe that the reason the soup ...
We live in one place now . We used to travel a lot .
Do you enjoy travel ? Nothing is as stimulating .
Alma is an unusual and beautiful name .
I 'm completely incapable of feeling aggression .
I can muster bureaucratic vengefulness ...
Here , we 're used to humiliation . We find it pleasurable ...
our fangs have remained intact .
Nowadays I want to be loved .
I once bought a painting from a well-known artist .
No comments now , Ernst !
Then I hung it upside down in my salon
and invited the artist over , along with a lot of people
who appreciated a good joke !
What a laugh we had then ! My God , how we laughed .
What do you say , sir Artist ? Wasn 't that a fine joke ?
The sores never heal , the pus never ceases to flow .
The infection is constant ... worse , faster , or slower towards the end .
The resistance of the heart decides the outcome .
I am constantly losing weight .
I travel the world over consulting specialists .
Sometimes the loss just stops ,
as it did this summer , but then it starts again .
My husband says it 's psychological ,
that it all began when we lost our money .
I embezzled the family fortune !
- I am the guilty one ! - We 've heard this ...
Why is Lindhorst sitting at our table ?
Can 't we just sell and leave ?
My fault , my fault , all this suffering .
My fault !
And then I shouted , " To hell with your medicines !
" It won 't go away . It will never go away !
" You must operate it away . You must just slice it off !
I am an old hag . There must be a limit ! "
And then he laughed and said ,
" No , madame Countess ,
I have never heard of any limits at all ! "
Yes , we have children , two boys .
Oh , no , not here . They live with an uncle ...
whom I believe is an acquaintance ?
I understand you know Veronica Vogler .
And very well , after what I 've heard .
An extraordinarily beautiful woman .
Veronica Vogler is charming !
Have you also met her ? Truly very charming .
No ?
Such hatred in those eyes !
Fredrik , the cacti you planted need to go !
I mean , I don 't enjoy them at all .
Actually , I am allergic to them .
You shouldn 't drag them along ...
All right , then ! We shall take coffee in the library .
- Help me a little . - Yes ...
Ladies and gentlemen ! Your attention !
May I offer a small puppet show to divert us ?
Can we extinguish the lights ?
There . Good .
Our guests of honor .
Come , come . There .
Music .
The Magic Flute is the greatest example .
One moment . I shall prove this presently .
Tamino 's guides have just left him in the dark courtyard
outside the Temple of Wisdom .
The young man cries in deepest despair ,
" Oh , eternal night , when shalt thou pass ?
When shall the light find my eyes ? "
The fatally ill Mozart secretly empathizes with these words .
And the reply from the chorus and orchestra is also ,
" Soon , soon , youth ... "
" or never . "
The most beautiful ,
the most shattering music ever written .
Tamino asks ,
" Is Pamina still alive ? "
The invisible chorus answers ,
" Pamina , Pamina is still alive . "
Hear ...
the strange and illogical but genial rhythm ...
Pami ... Na .
This is no longer the name of a young woman ...
but an incantation , a sorcerer 's formula .
A name text ... In short , a commission ...
and yet the highest manifestation of art .
Would you not agree , sir Artist ?
Pardon me .
I call myself " artist " for want of a better term .
There is nothing self-evident in my creative work
except the compulsion to do it .
Through no intent of my own ,
I have been pointed out as something apart ,
a five-legged calf , a monster .
I have never fought for that position ,
nor do I do so now to keep it .
Yet I may well at times
have felt the winds of megalomania sweep across my brow .
But I believe myself to be immune .
I need only for one second remind myself
of the utter unimportance of art in the human world
in order to cool myself down again .
But that does not mean the compulsion does not remain .
- So speaks a true artist ! - This is a real confession .
Magnificent ! What courage ! What clarity !
I suggest we raise our glasses to our artist ...
Not only a genius but a thinker , too !
I 'll be damned . I never would have suspected .
A flowering rose for your hair .
I must have scratched your cheek with my fingernail .
Let me see . I think it 's bleeding !
My handkerchief ... No , it is clean .
- Our artist is wounded . - I 'm so clumsy .
Stay calm now . You 've had too much to drink .
Come , stay by me for a little while now .
He doesn 't sleep at night . That 's why he can handle so little .
Come , let 's you and I get some fresh air .
The core of the castle dates from the 14th century .
It 's been in our family since the late 16th century .
We got a little over-excited . We live in such isolation .
We gave you a scare , but you won 't leave us now , will you ?
See there , Corinne , our castle is rather beautiful at night .
Yes , and that would be only at night .
My garter ! Look away now , Mr. Heerbrand !
- Where has Ernst gone ? - Ernst , friend , where are you ?
I just went off on my own a bit .
I 'm ashamed that the grounds are so unkempt .
Imagine ten years ago ... A paragon of garden art .
We never kiss . Have you thought of that ?
I can almost count our kisses .
There is something that frightens me almost to insanity .
I meet an unknown man in the road .
We converse .
Suddenly he turns and lands a vicious blow on my cheek !
His face is corpse white and his eyes are full of hatred .
And I understand nothing !
I only feel nauseated . My nose is bleeding ,
I stammer some silly excuses , horribly shaken ,
and I ask myself , when the man has disappeared ,
" Is this how it is ? Is this how it must be ? "
I can never forget the man 's eyes .
- The worst thing was ... - Nothing to worry about .
The blow , that blow ...
The worst of all was the man 's eyes ...
Are you leaving already ?
No , before you leave you must see
where I 've hung your painting of Veronica Vogler .
Alma , dear , come along , too .
She 's sleeping . We won 't disturb her .
- I 'm not sleeping . - Of course we 'll go along .
Come , then , both of you . Won 't take a moment .
Alma , you are about to see
something very beautiful your husband has made .
Here is the painting ,
directly in front of my bed .
I can see it each morning and night .
It has become like a part of my solitary life .
I love her .
How long did you live together ?
Pardon my asking something so personal .
- Five years . - Really ?
So he 's told you ?
He loved her , didn 't he ?
I didn 't need to ask that .
It was a first-class scandal at the time .
But so romantic ...
- Jealous ? - I don 't believe so .
My husband is quite jealous . Well , he 's an excellent lover .
Look at this mark , by the way .
It 's a scar from another man 's , shall we say , advances ?
A never-ending spring of renewed desire .
It 's all very trivial , of course , but it 's stimulating for me .
I need to come up with something new soon .
That mark can 't evoke fascinated admiration forever .
Can you help me ?
Alma , little dear , don 't get angry .
It was only in jest , of course , but it was a stupid joke .
Come , let 's go down to the others .
I have , in any case , bought a considerable piece of your husband ...
have I not ?
I have to confess that I have read your diary .
It makes me sick with fear !
Wait . Hear me out .
I need to tell you what I 've been thinking these past few days .
Here 's what I 've been thinking .
I see that something is going to happen , something evil ,
but I don 't know what to call it .
But if you think I 'm going to run away , I won 't !
I won 't run away no matter how frightened I am !
And one more thing .
They 're trying to separate us . They want you for themselves .
As long as I 'm with you , it 's much harder for them .
I won 't run away , no matter how much they try !
I 'll stay right where I am !
Johan , answer me !
- Do you hear how quiet it is ? - Yes , it is quiet .
There was a time when nights were for sleep ...
deep , dreamless sleep .
I cannot sleep .
I wake out of fear .
- Are you tired ? - No , not so terribly .
I have held vigil each night until daylight .
But this is the worst hour .
- Do you know what it 's called ? - No .
The old people used to call it the " Hour of the Wolf . "
It 's the hour at which most people die
and most children are born .
It 's now that the nightmares come to us .
- And if we are awake ... - We are afraid .
We are afraid .
What is it ?
Nothing . I just thought of something from my childhood .
It was some sort of punishment .
They threw me into a closet .
They shut the door .
It got quiet and dark .
I was horribly scared .
I kicked and pounded ,
because they had told me that a little person lived in that closet ...
who gnawed the toes off naughty children !
When I stopped pounding , I heard something rattling ,
and I knew my hour had come .
And in a kind of ... silent panic ,
I climbed onto some shelves
and tried to heave myself up by my hands .
Clothes tumbled around me .
I lost my grip and fell .
I swung my fists through the air
to shield myself from that little creature .
All the while I wailed in fear
and begged to be forgiven .
Finally the door opened and they let me step out into the daylight .
My father said ,
" Mother tells me you 're sorry . "
I said , " Yes , please forgive me . "
" Prepare the divan , then , " he said .
I went to the green divan in my father 's room ,
took some cushions , and stacked them .
Then I fetched the cane , unbuttoned my trousers ,
and leaned forward onto the cushions .
He said , " So how many strokes do you deserve ? "
And I answered , " As many strokes as possible . "
And he struck me with the cane ,
hard enough
but not more than I could bear .
When the caning was over ,
I went to Mother and asked ,
" Mother , can you forgive me now ? "
And she cried and said , " Of course I forgive you . "
Then she offered me her hand .
I kissed it .
Alma , are you listening ?
Are you asleep ?
No , I 'm awake .
My back aches .
To think it 's pitch black out still .
And so quiet ...
Strange , how the sea is never still .
Frightening somehow .
- Are you crying ? - No , I 'm not crying .
I 'm thinking of the child
and this great , quiet darkness .
Maybe it will never get light again .
Poor dear .
Give me your hand .
That 's much better .
Remember that day I said I 'd been snake bitten ?
Yes .
It wasn 't a snakebite .
Not a snakebite ?
I thought I 'd never tell a soul . I don 't even know if ...
You have to tell me !
You must never tell anyone else .
No , I promise , I 'll never tell anyone .
Remember that place by the cliffs ? We were there early this summer .
Yes .
Is the door locked securely ?
I checked twice .
Good morning !
Forgive my intrusion . A thousand pardons .
Looks like a storm coming ! I thought I 'd stop in for a moment .
I do also have an errand .
May I sit down ? This won 't take long .
I am to convey an invitation from the castle .
We had thought a little party ... No , not a big gathering .
Just something to distract those poor people
stuck in the castle year round , gnawing on each other !
As I said , not a large party .
But it will interest you that Veronica Vogler will be there .
And you will come too , yes ?
All right , then it 's agreed .
Incidentally , Von Merkens and I discussed the other day
your possible need to defend yourself .
I mean , from all the small game on the island .
That is all for the moment . Good morning , dear friends .
Hope to see you at our little party .
Shouldn 't you lock that weapon away ?
No , why ?
And what do we do now ?
You can tell me about Veronica Vogler .
What do you want me to say ?
That it went on for five years ?
You know that already .
We were discovered . It was a huge scandal .
The story was quieted down ... and then it ended .
That 's not what it says in your diary .
" My attachment to Veronica finally was painful for us both .
" I followed her in the streets , jealously spied on her .
" I believe my passion stimulated her ,
" but she was always passive and indecisive .
" We often ended in frightening confrontations
" far from any semblance of reason .
We traveled from town to town evading relatives or lawyers . "
No !
" We incarnated the words of the Bible ,
that man and woman shall be of one flesh . "
" Then her husband came and fetched her .
" I was sent to the hospital .
We did not see each other for several years . "
You said once that what you liked about me
was that God had made me in one piece ...
that I had whole feelings and whole thoughts .
You said it was important that there were people like me .
It sounded so lovely .
It made me so happy .
I was wrong .
I don 't understand a thing .
I don 't understand you !
You 're nothing but frightened !
And you want to stay here and possibly be killed !
Do you think I want to see you run after that woman ,
talking to those ghosts , guarding myself all the time ?
Do you think I want that ?
But I 'll stay .
Get up from the table now .
Now walk towards the door .
Now walk through it .
You go down the steps .
It 's not dark anymore . You can find your way .
How delightful ! Welcome !
Carry the tray , please .
Thank you . It 's my supper , you see .
Old Lindhorst , who is worldly , says that old harlots
have an unhealthy desire to fill their mouths and stomachs .
You really don 't care for anything ?
Wasn 't there to be a party here this evening ?
Not as far as I know .
No , don 't leave !
Please help me off with my stockings .
You don 't like to touch me .
I sense it clearly .
I don 't understand .
Veronica Vogler has come ...
and I 'm the only one who can tell you where she is .
Look closely at my feet , Artist .
Have you seen younger , tighter arches ?
Look closely . Look at my heel ,
how smooth and fine it is .
Such strong toes and beautiful nails .
Kiss my foot .
Yes , go ahead .
Yes , there !
You 've been sweet ,
and I 'll tell you where she is .
Try the west gallery .
She was there five minutes ago .
- Pardon me , I thought ... - You 're always welcome , dear friend .
You come , you go , you stay . You have complete freedom .
Let us speak openly as well .
You have come to find Veronica Vogler .
I should perhaps mention before you see her
that Veronica has been my mistress for several years .
She has kindly related in detail your common past .
I can assure you I suffer .
I shall be by your bed tonight .
Every word , every kiss , every movement across your bodies ...
Nothing will be spared me .
Come , I 'll show the way .
Oh , it 's only my jealousy . Please go away .
Yes , of course . Of course .
It 's Conductor Kreisler playing .
Conductor Kreisler is a master at his instrument .
Don 't you think Veronica has waited long enough ?
She began preparing for your visit already this morning .
She has become even more beautiful .
My husband is suffering .
He is jealous .
And your touching little companion ...
Three shots , one of them fatal .
Wonderful music .
I think I must take off my hat so I can hear better .
It really smells of glue !
Though she insists it is all synthetic .
Plain old glue is what it is . She can 't fool me .
We have our tricks , don 't we ?
Let 's see now if we 're presentable .
How pale you are , dear friend . What a sight !
Your lips are as blue as if you 'd eaten blueberries .
We must do something . Sit down here .
Let 's see what we can do .
Right .
A lovely cupid 's bow ...
A sensual lower lip is always titillating .
Your eyes are swollen and bloodshot .
This will soothe them .
Well , dear me .
And so , a few lines on the eyelids .
There now !
Some fresh color to your skin wouldn 't hurt .
Well , what next ? Yes , borrow my robe .
There and there ... and there .
And see there . It suits you , it suits you !
Wait , beautiful pajamas are called for on occasions such as this .
A nice perfume ? No ?
You prefer to smell of yourself , of course .
Each to his own scent , but a little ...
gives a scent anyway .
I knew it .
See yourself now in the mirror .
Now you are yourself
and yet not yourself ,
the ideal state for a meeting between lovers .
Come now ! This way !
There is her door .
You see what you want to see !
Veronica , no !
No , them ... Don 't pay attention to them !
I thank you ...
that the limit has finally been transgressed .
The mirror has been shattered .
But what do the splinters reflect ?
Can you tell me that ?
Yes , he fired three shots .
One scratched my arm . I still have a little scar .
I fell over from sheer terror .
I thought it best to lie still .
I heard him pace back and forth , behind and around the house ...
then he ran toward the path .
I stood up , went inside ,
washed off the blood , and put on a bandage .
Then I hid the pistol and sat down to wait .
He was gone some minutes , then he came running back .
I hid myself to be on the safe side .
He looked absolutely insane .
He walked around the cottage talking to himself ...
then he got out the diary and began to write .
He wrote for hours .
Then by mid-morning he packed his satchel
and headed off toward the woods .
I thought it best to follow him .
He might harm himself .
Don 't you see me ?
- Where is he ? - I know where you can find him .
Come .
Call to him , then .
Well , there is one thing I 've wondered .
Are you in a hurry ?
I 'd like to ask you something .
It 's like this .
Isn 't it true that when a woman has lived a long time with a man ...
isn 't it true she finally becomes like that man ?
Since she loves him
and tries to think like him
and see like him .
They say that it can change a person .
Was that why I began to see those ghosts ?
Or were they there anyway ?
I mean , if I 'd loved him less
and not bothered about everything there around him ...
could I have protected him better then ?
Or was it that I didn 't love him enough
that made me so jealous ?
Was that why those " cannibals , " as he called them ...
was that why we came to such grief ?
I thought I was so close to him .
Sometimes he said he was also close to me .
One time he said it with certainty .
If only I could have followed him , all the time .
There 's so much to keep pondering ...
so many questions , sometimes I don 't know which way is which ,
and I get completely ...